<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Of predestination [and] election made by Joh[a]n Lamberd minister of the church of Elham. Anno M.D.L.</title>
            <author>Lambert, John, Minister of Elham.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1550</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 15 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05039</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15181</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103827</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839572</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839572</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4004</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05039)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4004)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 70:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Of predestination [and] election made by Joh[a]n Lamberd minister of the church of Elham. Anno M.D.L.</title>
                  <author>Lambert, John, Minister of Elham.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In saynt Paules parysh by J. Mychell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Prynted at Ca[n]torbury :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1550?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴ C³.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Predestination --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4004:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:4004:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->
            <p>Of predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion &amp; election made by Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Lamberd miniſter of the church of Elham. Anno M.D.L.<lb/> 
               <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Non mortui laudabunt te domine.</l>
               <l>Sed nos qui viuimꝰ benedicimus domino.</l>
            </q>
            <p>I wryte vnto you babes, howe that youre ſynnes are forgeuen you for Chriſtes ſake.</p>
            <p>And nowe babes abyde in hym that when he ſhal appere we may be bolde, &amp; not be made aſhamed of hym at his commynge.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:4004:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:4004:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->
            <head>To the reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Moſt dere reader myne entent is not to Iudge any man, but that, when he hath red this lytle tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atyſe, he may conſulte or counſell with his owne conſcience and ſo examyne the ſame, whether he do lyue lyke a reprobate or one that is electe of God to ſaluacion, for the dedes of a reprobate are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfeſt. Alſo lykewyſe the dedes of the electe are not hydde. Therfore my councell is that no man dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute with God why he hath ordey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned the veſſelles of wrath to da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacion, yf he do S. Paule dothe make hym an anſwere. (Becauſe ſayth he that he myght declare the ryches of his glory on the veſſels of mercy whiche he had preparyd vnto glory) for the reprobates are
<pb facs="tcp:4004:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 17 -->
mynyſters vnto the ſaluacyon of the electe, which are Goddes wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kemanſhyp created in Chriſte Ieſus vnto good workes, vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche ſaythe ſaynt Paule, God ordeyned vs before that we ſhuld walke in them: He ſaythe more o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, by grace ye are made ſaue tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rough fayth that worketh by loue the whiche faythe is the gyfte of God, and as many as haue the ſame gyfte of God haue cauſe to prayſe the fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther and the ſone &amp; the holy ghoſt to whome be all honor and glory. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:4004:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 17 -->
            <head>Of predeſtinacion</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Od hathe no be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnynge nor ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhall haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge,<note place="margin">Gene. 7.</note> he maye do what he wyll and none but he. The bryghteſt aungell that euer was, was euer in Goddes ſyght before he was: The fouleſt deuyll that euer was, was euer in Goddes ſyght before he was.</p>
            <p>To conclude all thynges good and bad were euer preſently in the ſyghte of God or euer they were: For God dyd ſee thend or he dyd begyn any thynge. Alſo he dyd know by his preſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce who ſhulde goo the brode way that leadeth to perdicion. And who ſhoulde goo the ſtrayte waye that leadeth to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall lyfe.<note place="margin">Math. 7.</note> The Bleſſed and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecte
<pb facs="tcp:4004:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 18 -->
people of God,<note place="margin">Ephe. 1.</note> be and euer were in the ſyghte of God, before the world was layd and predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate thoroughe Ieſus Chriſte to be heyres vnto him ſelfe. Alſo the reprobates ſuche as ſhoulde be deſpiſers of goddes liuely worde, were in his ſight or euer they were borne, and or euer the worlde was layde, which are called the veſſels of wrath ordeined to dampnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Roma. 9.</note> The elect doeth humble him ſelfe lyke vnto the puplicane referring all thynges to the mercy of God. Sayinge theſe wordes. I poore ſinner do beleue iuſtly that Chriſt dyed for me and for as many as with aliuely fayth do confeſſe him to be the ſonne of God, and none that beleue in him periſh but haue eternall lyfe. Is it poſſyble that
<pb facs="tcp:4004:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 18 -->
the reprobate maye haue thys ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely fayth? No, but only aſhew thereof as Eſau flattered wyth Iacob to hys face, but ſekynge meanes to deſtroy him i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his hart.<note place="margin">Gene. 27.</note> Lykewyſe Iudas kyſſed Chriſte with his mouthe,<note place="margin">Abdy. 1.</note> yet he bare hym a falſe harte. For ſuch is the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of traytors and reprobates.</p>
            <p>The Pharyſeys in lyke manner aſked Chriſte yf they were blynd, ſpeakynge to him yroniuſly moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyngly. But Chriſte ſayde vnto them yf ye were blynde ye ſhoulde haue no ſynne. That is ye ſee the workes of God wrought by me, yet ye beleue me not and wyll not ſee, the cauſe is why,<note place="margin">Ihon. 1<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ye do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue, you be none of my ſhepe. So the reprobates maye ſee carnally, and not liuely, becauſe they be the
<pb facs="tcp:4004:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->
chyldren of perdicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and deſtitute of Goddes grace,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 2.</note> for Goddes worde hindreth and hurteth them for it is vnto theim an odoure of deathe. But the electe are ſure to haue thys lyuely faythe, for they hope to be ſaued by the paſſion of Chriſte only and bryngeth fourth the fruytes of faythe as they haue bynne taught by Chriſte and hys worde. For Goddes worde vnto them is a odoure of lyfe.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 2.</note> For vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them was Chriſt ſente in to the worlde to be their Sauiour. For the paſſion of Chriſte can not ſaue a reprobate, that is he that refuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the trueth and alwayes doeth ſtryue agaynſte the holy Ghoſte, whoſe dampnacion is iuſt &amp; true. For ſuche are da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pnable creatures knowne of God before the worlde
<pb facs="tcp:4004:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->
was layde and are called the veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of wrathe to declare Goddes glory on the veſſels of mercy. For theſe dampnable creatures that do perſeuer &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually do ſtryue agaynſt the trueth turne Goddeſt trueth in to a lye whych is bleſſed for euer. Amen.<note place="margin">Roma. 1.</note>
            </p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <p>Deus creauit Angelos quos ſciebat ruituros.<note place="margin">Auguſti.</note> Quare deus creauit illos quos ſciebat eſſe dampnandos. Reſpondeo,<note place="margin">Bonaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> quia ſi nullus creatus fuiſſet niſi ſaluandus, credidiſſent homines ſe ſaluari ex neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate non ex diuina gratia.</p>
               <p>Inquit,<note place="margin">Aug. de ci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uita. 22.</note> melius iudicauit deus de malis <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere bona quam mala non ſinere.</p>
            </q>
            <p>The electe alſo was predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate of God to be ſaued, but yet was not Chriſte promiſed to be their Sauioure, vnto ſuche tyme as Adam and Eue had offended god by diſobedience for after they had tranſgreſſed goddes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demente
<pb facs="tcp:4004:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 20 -->
god ſayd to the Serpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <note place="margin">Gene. 3.</note>Inimiticias ponam inter te et mulierem, et ſemen tuum et ſemen illius, ipſa con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teret caput tuum, et tu inſidiaberis calta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neo eius.</q>
            <p>That is, I wyll put enmytye betwene the and the womam, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene thy ſeed &amp; her ſeede the ſame ſhall breake thy heade and thou ſhalte treade on his heele. Here Chriſte was promyſed to breake the Serpentes heade for he was the very ſeed. Therfore yf Adam and Eue had not tea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Chriſte ſhould not haue dyed, nowe ſeinge they did offende they and all their poſteryte were infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with that contagyouſe poyſin of ſynne. There was no remedy but Chriſte muſte nedes dye, or els we ſhould haue byn dampned perpetually. Here maye we ſe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4004:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 20 -->
that Adams diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce dampned vs all,<note place="margin">Roma. 5.</note> yet we our ſelues wrought euyll. Therfore ſeynge we were the cauſers of Chriſtes death god myght haue dampned vs Iuſtly, although he elected vs before the worlde was made.<note place="margin">Gene. 2.</note> But god will be founde true and all men liars. For Chriſtes obedience ſaueth vs all,<note place="margin">Roma. 5.</note> yet we oure ſelues worke any good. Therfore nowe are we bounde and doubble bounde to geue God all honour and prayſe and to loue hym aboue meaſure, becauſe God fyrſt predeſtinate vs &amp; elected vs in hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde was made y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhulde be ſayntes,<note place="margin">Ephe. 1.</note> for Chriſte was predeſtinate to be the Sonne of God.<note place="margin">Peter. 1.</note> And than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge loſt thorough ſynne, yet god knowynge by his preſcience ſuche
<pb facs="tcp:4004:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 21 -->
thinges would come to paſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ephe. 1.</note>Saynct Paule ſayeth God ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vs before thoroughe Ieſus Chriſt to be heyres vnto hym ſelfe accordynge to the pleaſure of hys will. Here God hathe gyuen vs Chriſt to redeme vs by whom we haue redempcion thoroughe hys bloude euen the forgeueneſſe of ſynnes. He hath quickned vs alſo that were deade in treſpas and ſynne.<note place="margin">Ephe. 2.</note> Nowe ſhall you ſee that it is neceſſary the elect ſuch as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue in Chriſte with aliuely faythe ſhould not blame God becauſe he hathe predeſtinate ſome to be the chyldren of perdicion, onleſſe they would be ſory for their owne ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion, he ordeined ſome to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhed accordynge to their dedes. The electe are punyſhed many
<pb facs="tcp:4004:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 21 -->
times with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyre of aduerſytye to trye them &amp; to purge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they maye brynge fourthe muche fruet althoughe they fall be frayltie,<note place="margin">Iohn. 15.</note> as none can lyue without ſynne,<note place="margin">pſal. 107.</note> yet are they puniſhed with mercy,<note place="margin">Iohn. 1.</note> but the reprobate that doeth euyll of purpoſe and wyll ſhewe no mercy therfore he ſhall haue iuſtice with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mercy.<note place="margin">Sala. 12.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Iames. 2.</note> Who ſhoulde haue byn miniſters vnto death of ſuche a kynges ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne as he was but ſuch as were caſtawayes ordeyned of God to be the chyldren of perdicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and mete for nothyng els.<note place="margin">Iohn. 16.</note> What ſhould a carpenter make of rotten wood, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> potter with brutle clay that wyll ſerue for no other thing but be caſte awaye or to be put to ſome other vyle purpoſe? Who can let the carpenter or the potter
<pb facs="tcp:4004:8"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 22 -->
to vſe ſuche thynges as them lyſt. Notwithſtandynge ſuche as we named reprobates before were mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyſters vnto oure ſaluacyon, that then were, is nowe, or ſhall beleue in Chriſt with aliuely faith. Like<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wyſe Pharoes harte was harde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſhew the glory of God and his mighty power to al the world, that were ſythes that tyme,<note place="margin">Exo. 9.</note> and is to come, for in euery age god hath ſhewed hys wonders becauſe he woulde be knowene that there is none lyke vnto him. Now yf they had not put Chriſt vnto death we had not byn redemed. But howe maye we know the reprobate now frome the electe. Theſe thynges do I ſpeake vnto thoſe that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe Goddes truethe, whiche are forbydden to company with for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicators,
<pb facs="tcp:4004:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 22 -->
and ſpecyally from ſuch a brother that is a fornicator an extorſionar, or couetouſe, a reiler, or a drounkarde (Saynct Paule ſayeth) with hym that is ſuche ſee that ye eate not. In this place.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.</note> S. Paule doethe ſeperate the one fro the other, to thentente we ſhoulde put awaye frome vs all euyll, for them that are withoute God ſhall Iudge. So I in lyke caſe here, haue ſet vp a glaſſe to thentent yf any loke theron eſpye difformitye vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> himſelf it may geue hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to waſhe hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe with the wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter of life, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to examen hys con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Gods liuely word whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he lyue according to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion or lyke a reprobate. The reprobate hathe a ſl<gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap>nge ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, and is full, o<gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="4+ letters">
                  <desc>••••…</desc>
               </gap>tye ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedyng enuiouſe, <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap>e, neuer
<pb facs="tcp:4004:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 23 -->
confirmable to honeſtie,<note place="margin">Gene. 4.</note> withoute repentance,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ohn. 10.</note> preſumynge to much on goddes mercy, alwayes incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtante,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ob. 15.</note> repungnante agaynſte the trueth,<note place="margin">Mat. 26.</note> full of blaſphemy a fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat of mammon as one that is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſatiffied but alwayes poore &amp; nedy in his harte &amp; ſo dyeth with nothynge. All theſe thynges happen to them that God gyueth vp to do their awne wylles; for with thys plague innumerable haue byn caſtawaye. Theſe are the very tokens of a reprobate, &amp; with ſuch we ſhould not company nor eate, ſo longe as they perſeuer in that wycked eſtate. Lykewyſe the electe are knowen by thir fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, for they are Goddes worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhy<gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="4+ letters">
                  <desc>••••…</desc>
               </gap>ted in Chriſt Ieſus to good <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> vnto the whyche
<pb facs="tcp:4004:9"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 23 -->
God ordeyned theim before, that they ſhould walke in them. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is impoſſible that the elect ſhoulde be dampned, nowe ſeyng that God wyll not forſake hys e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecte ſuche as haue a liuely faythe in Chriſte hys deare ſonne, and a ſure hope to receiue his promiſis, bringyng forth the frutes of faith that worketh by loue: That is we laboure not for rewarde to the entente he myghte make vs hys heyres for that is ours all redye yf we beleue his promiſis, but we muſt be ſeruauntes to al men that be our brothers in Chriſt, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſter vnto theim the fruytes of faythe in all their nede. Lyke as Chriſte God and man mynyſtred vnto vs when we had moſt nede, &amp; loke what trybulacyons or my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries
<pb facs="tcp:4004:10"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 24 -->
they ſuffre, whether it be hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, colde, pouertie, or any other aduerſitie, lette vs thynke it to be ours, and ſo to beare the croſſe of Chriſte paciently to gethers.</p>
            <p>Nowe let euery man conſulte or counſell with his awne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and examyne hym ſelfe whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he haue this lyuelye fayth or not, yf he haue that gyfte of God, it is a very ſure token that he is the very electe of God. Therfore neuer clymbe any hygher or ſerche any further, why God hathe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinate ſome, to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyldren of perdicion, wherby they might put any blame in God, &amp; thynke that he lacketh charytie, whoſe iuſtyce and iudgement can neuer be done but with loue,<note place="margin">Iohn. 4.</note> for he is very loue it ſelfe. But rather let vs prayſe
<pb facs="tcp:4004:10"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 24 -->
his holy name becauſe he hathe called vs to ſo bleſſed an eſtate, and moreouer becauſe he is Iuſt and holy, and knoweth beſt what is to be done for vs. Alſo let vs geue hartye thankes to Chriſt for oure redempcion: And let vs ſyng ioyfully to the holi ghoſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he may geue his clere lyght to ſuche as be deſyrus to knowe the truthe of Goddes lyuely word, to whome be all honor and glory Amen.</p>
            <closer>Geue prayſe to God that worketh all, in all.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:4004:11"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 25 -->
            <head>The Author.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue declared my iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment which is but ſmall, concernynge predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion and the foreknoweledge of God. Therfore gentle reader ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte my good wyll, and where as you ſe a faute in my buyldynge that frames not to youre mynde, accepte my meanyng I pray you, and cauyll not, for I am not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynat, but wyllynge to knowe the truthe: And as nyghe as I canne Goddes lyuely worde ſhall be the foundacion wheron I entende to buylde at any tyme. Euery good gyfte, and euery perfyte gyfte, is from aboue, and commeth downe from the father of lyghte. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs alwayes thynke that the goodnes that we haue or ſhall haue commeth of God and not of
<pb facs="tcp:4004:11"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 25 -->
our ſelues to whome be all honor, and glory.</p>
            <closer>AMEN<lb/>
Geue the prayſe to God.<lb/>
Domine ſaluum fac regem.</closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>Non mortui laudabunt te domine: neque</l>
                  <l>omnes qui deſcendunt in infernum.</l>
                  <l>Sed nos qui viuimus benedicimus domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no:</l>
                  <l>ex hoc nunc et vſque in ſeculum.</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Prynted at Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>torbury in ſaynt Paules paryſh by I. Mychell.<lb/> 
               <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
